Guide to the Paul Gillespie Collection of New York World's Fair Materials 1936-2010 PR 283
New-York Historical Society
Paul Gillespie collection of New York World's Fair materials
1936-2010 (Bulk 1939-1940)
New-York Historical Society
PR 283
16.87 Linear feet
Photographs and ephemera from the 1939-40 New York World's Fair collected by Paul Gillespie.
Provenance
Gift of Paul Gillespie, 2011.
Access
The collection is open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been photocopied or microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format; microfilm can be made available through Interlibrary Loan.
Permission to reproduce or quote in publication
Application to use images from this collection for publication should be made in writing to the Department of Rights and Reproductions, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024. Permission to reproduce or quote text from this collection in a publication must be requested from and granted in writing by the Library Director, The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, New York, NY 10024.
Biographical Note
Paul Gillespie (1927-2011) was born and raised in Miami, Florida, but he relocated to New York City, where he lived for almost 50 years in an apartment on the upper west side of Manhattan. A graduate of the University of Miami and Columbia University, Mr. Gillespie served first in the U.S. Army and then with the U.S. State Department before becoming a teacher with the Pelham, New York, public school system. It is doubtful that Mr. Gillespie attended the 1939-40 New York World's Fair, but he developed a lifelong interest and collected an impressive assortment of photographs, scrapbooks, pamphlets, guidebooks, menus and other fair-related ephemera. While family members recall walks with Mr. Gillespie around the Flushing Meadows fairgrounds, it is unclear what motivated his fascination with the fair. However, it is apparent from the notebooks, related ephemera and books he acquired that Mr. Gillespie read widely on the subject and travelled to regional libraries and historical societies conducting research.
Historical Note
Located on over 1200 acres in Flushing Meadows, Queens, the New York World's Fair ran for two seasons, from April 30, 1939 to October 31, 1939, and then reopening from May 11, 1940, to October 27, 1940. Originating from a desire to revitalize the Depression-weary spirit and economy of New York City and the nation, the fair attracted the participation of sixty nations, thirty-three U.S. states and drew approximately forty-five million visitors. The fair's first season was instilled with optimism about the capacity for the present to give rise to a prosperous "World of Tomorrow." However, towards the conclusion of its first season, this hopeful outlook would take on an ironic aspect as war loomed and the fair struggled to turn a profit.
Led by Grover Whalen and many of the most prominent figures in New York economic and political life, the fair organizers employed the latest ideas in design and marketing to make the fair a reality. Whalen travelled extensively and convinced countries as diverse as the Soviet Union, El Salvador, Iraq and Japan to participate. The fair's Board of Design featured prominent modernist architects and industrial designers, such as Walter Dorwin Teague, Norman Bel Geddes, Alvar Aalto and Wallace Harrison, who oversaw the creation of a clean, streamlined vision of tomorrow. Their design theme was most dramatically and famously embodied in the 700-foot tall Trylon and 180-foot diameter Perisphere that formed the center point of the fair grounds.
The fair's international pavilions strove to acquaint visitors with the nations of the world and stressed the virtues of cooperation and interdependence. Exhibit halls sponsored by corporations such as General Motors, Westinghouse, and AT&T combined marketing with technology demonstrations and other spectacles to create a promising vision of the future in which their innovative products would play an essential role. Meanwhile, the fair's "Amusement Zone" offered visitors thrill rides, dazzling shows, carnival attractions, sideshow novelties and risque thrills. The fair also featured industrial and technology exhibits, several gardens, an art gallery, statues and sculptures of many sizes, fountains and pools, and a model "town of tomorrow." A sense of wonder also stemmed from the cutting edge technologies that were showcased at the fair. While taken for granted today, color photography, television broadcasts, air conditioning, and the use of large scale lighting employed for dramatic effect, were some of the new marvels that were demonstrated for the first time.
The fair was not without controversy and received its share of criticism from contemporary critics. The total cost of admission and spending a day at the fair was deemed prohibitively expensive for many Americans. Both this cost and the manner in which the fair was marketed were criticized as having an exclusionary effect towards African Americans and ethnic minorities. The NAACP and Urban League protested unfair hiring practices and insufficient representation of African Americans in the fair's exhibits. Social critics also expressed concern that the fair's ideals were compromised by the prevalence of consumerism and crass amusements.
By the time the fair's second season opened, many of the participating nations were engulfed in the Second World War, leading some to either withdraw from the fair or causing their delegations to become exiles in America. In response, the slogan of the fair was changed to "For Peace and Freedom" and new patriotic themes prevailed. In an effort to attract more visitors, the price of admission was lowered and a greater emphasis was placed on marketing the fair's amusements. Despite these changes the fair did not last past its second season and would ultimately declare bankruptcy. However, the legacy of the fair would remain in the post-war memories of Americans who would go on to create a cultural landscape that in many ways resembled the prosperous, streamlined, middle-class world that the fair had imagined.
Scope and Content
The Paul Gillespie Collection of New York World Fair Materials consists largely of photographs, post cards, scrapbooks, photo albums and ephemera that document the 1939-40 New York World's Fair. The collection was assembled over the course of Mr. Gillespie's lifetime and represents a diverse assortment of items from a variety of sources. In particular, the collection contains a large number of amateur photographs that offer a contrasting perspective to the iconographic pictures taken by professionals. Some of these snapshots depict rare glimpses inside exhibits and shows. The collection also contains over 200 color photographs that offer a richer look of how the fair truly appeared. Also noteworthy is an assortment of menus taken from many of the fair's restaurants and a scrapbook that contains both a detailed diary from multiple visits to the fair and a unique collection of ephemera.
A small amount of material relating to the 1964-65 New York World's Fair, the Golden Gate International Exposition and other world fairs is also found in this collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by format and has been divided into seven series:
Missing Title
Series I. Photographs
Series II. Post Cards
Series III. Scrap Books and Photo Albums
Series IV. Ephemera
Series V. Correspondence and Notebooks
Series VI. Publications
Series VII. Oversize Material
Related Materials
Other photographs and prints of the New York World's Fairs can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020), the Postcard File (PR 065) and the Album File (PR 002) in the New-York Historical Society's Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections. There is also a large collection of World's Fair books and ephemera in the library's general collections. To search the general collection, click here.
References
Harrison, Helen A., and Joseph P. Cusker. 1980. Dawn of a new day: the New York World's Fair, 1939/40. Flushing, N.Y.: Queens Museum.
"The Iconography of Hope: The 1939-40 New York World's Fair," accessed July 21, 2011, http://xroads.virginia.edu/~1930s/display/39wf/front.htm.
"African Americans in 'The World of Tomorrow': 1939," accessed July 21, 2011, http://www.jimcrowhistory.org/resources/lessonplans/hs_es_newyorkfair.htm.
"Clash in the world of tomorrow," accessed July 21, 2011, http://www.sjsu.edu/faculty/wooda/149/149syllabus12.html.
Amusement parks -- History; Burlesque (Theater) -- History.; Color slides.; Exhibition buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Freak shows -- United States -- History.; Gelatin silver prints.; International relations and culture.; Lighting, Architectural and decorative -- History -- 20th century.; Magazines (periodicals).; Menus.; Pamphlets.; Photograph albums.; Photographic prints.; Picture postcards.; Printed ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Stereographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- History.; Queens (New York, N.Y.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda -- Public opinion.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111]
- Series I. Photographs, 1936-1940
  See Also
  Series VII. Oversize Materials
  Scope and Content
  There are approximately 3,500 loose photographs in a wide variety of formats, from as small as 1.5 x 2.25 inches to as large as 16 x 20 inches, but most are between 2.75 x 4-9/16 inches and 8 x 10 inches. The majority of photographs are gelatin silver prints, but there are more than two hundred color photographs as well. Also within this series are an assortment of stereographs and twenty-six, 4 x 5 inch Kodachrome direct positive transparencies.
  Due to the range of formats and levels of identification, this series has been further divided into nine subseries:
  World's Fair Publicity: 1939 - 1940 Press Photographs General Electric Snapshot Contest The Bettmann Archive Identified Photographers Unidentified Photographers Photographs from other Institutions Oversize Stereographs
  There are approximately 3,500 loose photographs in a wide variety of formats, from as small as 1.5 x 2.25 inches to as large as 16 x 20 inches. The majority of photographs are gelatin silver prints, but there are more than two hundred color photographs as well. Also within this series are an assortment of stereographs and twenty-six, 4 x 5 inch Kodachrome direct positive transparencies.
  Missing Title
  Subseries I. World's Fair Publicity
  Subseries II. Press Photographs
  Subseries III. General Electric Snapshot Contest
  Subseries IV. The Bettmann Archive
  Subseries VI. Unidentified Photographers
  Subseries V. Identified Photographers
  Subseries VII. Photographs from other Institutions
  Subseries VIII. Other World Fairs
  Subseries IX. Stereographs
  - Subseries I. World's Fair Publicity
    This subseries contains a variety of 8 x 10 inch photographs taken by New York World's Fair Corporation photographers and disseminated by the New York's World's Fair Publicity / Public Relations Office. Many include narrative material on the reverse side of the photograph.
    - Publicity Photos, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Publicity Photos, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Subseries II. Press Photographs
    This subseries consists of 8 x 10 inch photographs taken by news corporations or agencies.
    - ACME, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    - Associated Press, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    - Herarld Tribune, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    - International News, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wide World Photos, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subseries III. General Electric Snapshot Contest, 1939-1940
    This subseries consists of amateur photographs entered in a contest sponsored by General Electric.
    - General Electric Snapshot Contest, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IV. The Bettmann Archive
    This subseries consists of 8 x 10 inch photographs from the Bettmann Archive.
    - The Bettmann Archive, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries V. Identified Photographers
    This subseries consists mostly of 8 x 10 inch photographs bearing ownership stamps from individual photographers, including some known professionals. The largest collection is from Underwood & Underwood, a prominent commercial photography company that was employed by the World's Fair Corporation Publicity Department. The Underwood & Underwood file also contains a packaged collection titled, "Official Photographs New York World's Fair 1939." Other significant items in this subseries include nearly 200 color photographs taken by Conrad H. Ruppert using Kodak's new Kodachrome transparency film. There are also a number of aerial photographs taken by Rudy Arnold and McLaughlin Air Service that show the fair grounds prior to and during construction.
    - Rudy Arnold, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    - H. Baranger, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    - George A. Douglas, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    - Samuel H. Gottscho, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    - McLaughlin Air Sevice, 1936,1939 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    - Conrad H. Ruppert, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6-9)
    - A. F. Sozio, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
    - Underwood & Underwood, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-13)
    - Underwood & Underwood, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Carl Van Vechten, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Photographers, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subseries VI. Unidentified Photographers
    This subseries is the largest part of the Gillespie collection and consists of a large assortment of photographs by unknown photographers, covering a variety of subjects, styles and formats. The photographs capture almost every aspect of the fair, including pictures of the fair under construction and images inside exhibits and shows. Many photographs have a distinctly amateur quality in their choice of subject and composition, but a significant number demonstrate an advanced level of skill.
    Photographs in this subseries are arranged by size and format. If sleeved, they are done so back-to-back if no useful information is written on the reverse. Large photographs are mostly 8 x 10 inches or similar in size. Medium photographs are mainly in the range of 4 x 6 inches to 5 x 7 inches; Box 5, folders 6 through 8 were originally bound together as a single album, but were rehoused for conservation purposes. Included in the medium category are three folders that originally came from a single bound collection of vinyl sleeves. Small photographs are mostly smaller than 4 x 6 inches. This category also includes two sets of small souvenir photo cards that are still in their original packaging. Color positives are twenty-six, 4 x 5 Kodachrome direct positive transparencies.
    - Large Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Large Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-7)
    - Large Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Large - Color, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    - Medium Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5-8)
    - Medium Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - Medium Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - Medium Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Medium - Color, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 4)
    - Small Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-7)
    - Small Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-8)
    - Small Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-7)
    - Small Photographs, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-6)
    - Small - Color, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 7)
    - Color Positives, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 8)
  - Subseries VII. Photographs from other Institutions (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-10)
    This subseries contains a variety of photographs that Paul Gillespie obtained from the collections of other institutions.
    - Photographs from other Institutions, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-10)
  - Subseries VIII. Other World Fairs
    This subseries contains a small number of photographs that are from the 1964-65 New York World's Fair, the Golden Gate International Exposition or other world fairs. The photographs are a mixture of color or black & white, small and medium size prints.
    - Other World Fairs (Offsite-box 13, Folder 11)
  - Subseries IX. Stereographs
    This subseries contains several varieties of stereograph. One set is still housed in its original wooden box, along with an insert that reads, "Stereo Pictures of The New York World Fair" and "Rogers and Rogers" of Newark, NJ. Although this set appears to be commercially produced, the captions and numbering are handwritten. There are an additional 72 loose stereographs and a single "Stereovue" card that depicts 3 images.
    - Stereographs (1 of 2), 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 14)
    - Stereographs (2 of 2), 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 15)
- Series II. Post Cards
  This series contains approximately 200 picture postcards from the New York World Fair, the majority of which are unused souvenir cards. Five postcards are amateur photographic postcards.
  - Post Cards, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 15)
- Series III. Scrap Books and Photo Albums
  This series contains twelve photo albums and three scrap books of unknown origin that were collected by Paul Gillespie. Most of the albums and scrapbooks appear to have been created by different people who attended the New York World's Fair and contain a mix of amateur and souvenir photographs, memorabilia, newspaper clippings and some non-world's fair material. Of particular interest is a "Diary and Scrap Book" that includes diary style entries documenting a visitor's thirty-three separate visits to the fair over the course of its two seasons, as well as a collection of fair ephemera.
  A series of photographs that were originally in vinyl sleeves and bound as an album, were rehoused in archival sleeves and are located in box 5, folders 6-8.
  - Photo Album 1 (Offsite-box 16)
  - Photo Album 2 (Offsite-box 17)
  - Photo Albums 3-4 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Photo Albums 5-11 (Offsite-box 19)
  - Diary and Scrap Book (Offsite-box 19)
  - Scrap Books 1-2 (Offsite-box 20)
- Series IV. Ephemera
  See also
  This series contains a variety of ephemera and memorabilia from the New York World's Fair, including a large number of pamphlets, brochures and booklets from the fair's shows, corporate exhibits, and government pavilions. Of particular interest is a collection of menus from many of the fair's restaurants.
  - Corporations, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-3)
  - Menus, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 4-5)
  - Nations, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6-7)
  - Nations, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - U.S. Cities and States, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 4-6)
- Series V. Correspondence and Notebooks
  This series contains two notebooks, one piece of correspondence and some associated ephemera. The notebooks mostly contain handwritten records of Mr. Gillespie's collection activities and chronological notes on daily World's Fair events. The notebooks also contain a variety of loose ephemera from his research activities. The correspondence documents the results of a 2010 auction of some of Mr. Gillespie's World Fair collection. It is unclear how much or how often Mr. Gillespie sought to sell parts of his collection.
  - Correspondence and Notebooks, 2010 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Publications
  This series contains a wide variety of books and periodicals that cover an assortment of world fair related topics. Many items deal exclusively with the 1939-40 New York World's Fair, but others either survey world fairs generally or relate to a different fair entirely.
  - New York World's Fair Corporation, 1939,1941 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - City of New York, 1939 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 3)
  - Museum Exhibit Books, 1980, 1984, 1990 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 4)
  - Periodicals, 1938-1940 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 5-7)
  - Picture Books, 1977, 2002 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-2)
  - Souvenir Books, 1939-1940, 1973 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3-4)
  - Other World Fairs, 1901, 1932, 1964-1965, 1985 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5-7)
  - Misscellaneous and Oversize Books, 1893-1894, 1941, 1962, 1966, 1978, 1981, 1985-1986, 1988-1989, 1995, 1999 (Offsite-box 25)
- Series VII. Oversize Materials, 1939, 1986, 1989
  Scoep and Content
  This series includes oversize materials from Series I. Photographs; Series V. Ephemera; and Series VI. Publications.
  Noteworthy items include, "Time Tears On," a souvenir book made for and by New York World's Fair employees, and the "U.S. Camera, World's Fair Issue," which contains an interesting collection of fair photography.
  - Oversize Materials (Offsite-box 26)